<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at Guild-Hall Chappel upon the 30th of September, 1683 by Benjamin Calamy ...</title>
            <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31841</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5722</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13689431</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13689431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101388</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31841)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101388)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 840:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and the Court of Aldermen, at Guild-Hall Chappel upon the 30th of September, 1683 by Benjamin Calamy ...</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Benjamin, 1642-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans III, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:101388:1"/>
            <head>Pritchard Mayor.</head>
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Martis ſecund. die Octob.</hi> 1683. <hi>An. Reg. Regis</hi> Car. 2. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, &amp;c.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Court doth deſire Dr. <hi>Calamy</hi> to Print his Sermon Preached at the <hi>Guild-Hall</hi> Chappel on <hi>Sunday</hi> Morning laſt, before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>WAGSTAFFE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101388:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Lord Mayor, And the Court of ALDERMEN, AT <hi>Guild-Hall Chappel,</hi> Upon the 30th of <hi>September,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>By <hi>BENJAMIN CALAMY,</hi> D.D. One of His Majeſties Chaplains in Ordinary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:101388:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101388:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Romans III. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And not rather, as we be ſlanderouſly report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and as ſome affirm that we ſay, let us do evil that good may come? Whoſe Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is juſt.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is on all hands agreed that the Doctrine, from which was raiſed this Impious and Damnable Concluſion mentioned in my <hi>Text, Let us do evil that good may come,</hi> and on the account of which it was father'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>St. Paul</hi> as his Judgment and Opinion, was what he had ſome time taught concerning the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration of the Glory of the Divine Goodneſs and Mercy, in pardoning the greateſt ſins of Men. That which moſt prejudiced the <hi>Jews</hi> againſt this great Apoſtle, was his Preaching the Goſpel to the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> his departing from, and rejecting his obſtinate unbelieving Country-men, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the uncircumciſed Heathen into the Church, tho' they had been guilty of the groſſeſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101388:3"/>and other enormous Vices which then reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed amongſt them, mentioned in the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Epiſtle. In defence of himſelf <hi>St. Paul</hi> uſed to plead, that the more heinous and provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſins of the Heathen World were, the more glorious and reſplendent was the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Divine Goodneſs, in offering them Pardon and Salvation upon the Terms of the Goſpel; and that it was the incurable perverſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>Jews,</hi> who would not believe in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which gave occaſion to this magnifying of Gods Grace towards the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now theſe two things the Enemies of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanity were ready to conclude from this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>St. Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. If this be ſo, that the ſins of Men give oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the further manifeſtation of Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and infinite Mercy, why then ſhould God puniſh the <hi>Jews</hi> or others for thoſe ſins which thus tend to his Glory? <hi>If our unrighteouſneſs,</hi> v. 5. <hi>commend the righteouſneſs of God, what ſhall we ſay? Is God unrighteous who taketh Vengeance? (I ſpeak as a man):</hi> that is, I only now recite an Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſome Men are apt to make againſt my Doctrine; Can God in juſtice take vengeance of our Unrighteouſneſs, when that ſerves to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and magnifie his own Righteouſneſs?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101388:3"/>
            <p>The ſame falſe Inference he repeats again, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>If the truth of God hath more abounded through my lie unto his Glory, why yet am I alſo judged as a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner?</hi> That is, If Gods faithfulneſs in performing his Promiſes made of old hath more abundantly appeared by reaſon of the <hi>Jews</hi> infidelity, if their refuſing the Goſpel hath contributed ſo much to the Honour of God, and the fuller diſcovery of his Grace towards Mankind, why then are they complained of, and condemned as Offenders?</p>
            <p>To this Objection the Apoſtle doth not think fit to give an elaborate Anſwer, but only expreſſeth his juſt deteſtation of any ſuch wicked Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as ſome ill Men would draw from his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. <hi>God forbid: For then how ſhall God judge the World?</hi> Far be it from me to aſſert any thing that ſhould in the leaſt reflect upon the Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Righteouſneſs of the Supream Judge of the World.</p>
            <p>The great God, who at firſt brought light out of darkneſs, and beautiful Order out of indigeſted Chaos, who by an Inviſible and Omnipotent Hand turns and winds all Things and Actions how he pleaſeth, and makes them often eventually ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervient and effectual to Ends clean contrary to their own proper tendency, and the intention of the ſubordinate Agents, will ſo manage and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101388:4"/>even Sins and Impieties, the Rage and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, the Plots and Stratagems of wicked Men and Devils, that they ſhall all in the upſhot conſpire to the advancing and ſetting forth his own Glory: But in the mean time this is no thanks to wicked Men, nor any excuſe of their ſin; but is to be aſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſolely to the irreſiſtible Power, and skilful Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Almighty Governour and Diſpoſer of all things both in Heaven and Earth. What Men Act purely to gratifie their own Luſts, to ſatiate their Revenge, or in order to the compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their Ambitious, Covetous, or any other evil or miſchievous Deſigns, may yet be ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and controuled by the Wiſe Providence of God, as that at laſt it ſhall bring Honour to his Name, and great Benefit to others: But ſtill the wickedneſs, the guilt of the Actors themſelves, is not in the leaſt abated or mitigated by this good Effect, which follows wholly againſt their will and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give an inſtance of this in that which is at preſent the great ſubject of our thoughts and diſcourſe. It is to be hoped, that our gracious God, who hath ſo wonderfully revealed the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and black Conſpiracies of deſperate Men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Perſon of our deareſt Soveraign and his Government, will after ſuch a manner diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101388:4"/>their Bloody Devices, as not only to prevent the intended miſchief, but alſo to make this Helliſh Plot it ſelf in the end contribute to the greater ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our Prince, and to the eſtabliſhment of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment both in Church and State, and that it ſhall ſerve to ſtrengthen and confirm that, which it was meant to ruine and overthrow: But all this doth not in the leaſt excuſe or juſtifie the Plotters themſelves, who juſtly ſuffer the utmoſt Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, notwithſtanding this advantage we may poſſibly through Gods infinite Wiſdom, and the Care of our Governours, reap from their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and Damnable Enterpriſes. Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> were worthily puniſhed for their obſtinate unbelief, though God without their knowledge, and againſt their deſign, made it an occaſion of diſplaying his Grace and Mercy to the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. A further and worſe inference (if there can be worſe) drawn from <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Doctrine, was this, If the Glory of God is ſo much advanced by the ſins of Men, let us then ſin freely without any dread or re morſe, for what need we fear or ſcruple doing that, from which ſo great good doth come? By this means we may do ſervice and bring Honour to God, ſince the greater our ſins are, the more will they illuſtrate and commend Gods Mercy in pardoning of them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101388:5"/>
            <p>Now this the Apoſtle in my Text firſt tells them is a <hi>Slander,</hi> or <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> as the Original word ſignifies, a ſcandalous imputation faſtned upon him and his Doctrine, which he abhorr'd: Then he Cenſures the Doctrine it ſelf as Damnable, <hi>whoſe Damnation is juſt.</hi> Which words may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie either of theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If you refer them to the former part of the Verſe, to thoſe Slanderers of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Doctrine, then they ſignifie that ſuch Men who thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly pervert and abuſe the Grace of God, by putting falſe Conſtructions upon, and drawing ſuch impious Conſequences from it, are guilty of a moſt Pernicious and Dangerous ſin.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you refer them, as many do, and as I ſhall now underſtand them, to the wicked reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution ſet down in the <hi>Text, Let us do evil that good may come;</hi> then they ſignifie that it is a Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſin to commit any Evil, though thereby the greateſt Good might be obtained; which is the Propoſition I ſhall now Diſcourſe of; That we muſt not venture to do the leaſt Evil, no not for the ſake of the greateſt Good; and I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident you will all readily grant, that this point is very ſeaſonable now to be inſiſted upon.</p>
            <p>For we need not Travel into Foreign Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, we need not conſult the Chronicles of paſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101388:5"/>Ages, nor be beholden to Ancient Records, to fetch thence Examples of thoſe who have done the vileſt and lewdeſt things imaginable, and yet have cloaked all, and defended themſelves by this Colourable Pretence, That what they did was for the Glory and Service of God, and the Good of his People. We have had too many ſad In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this amongſt our ſelves in this laſt Age. For have not the moſt Execrable Murders, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Villanies been acted in this Nation, and yet all pretended to be done for Gods ſake, for the preſervation of Religion and the Goſpel, and for the Safety and Liberty of the People? The old Wheadling Pretences of all Sedition and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. But I ſhall not look back to former Times.</p>
            <p>Have we not at this preſent Day heard of Men, who have undertaken the Aſſaſſination of the moſt Gracious and Merciful Prince that ever wielded the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Sceptre, and of his Royal Brother, the overturning the preſent Government, and bringing in all Confuſion and Anarchy, and God knows what, (for no one can tell, and it makes every Honeſt mans Heart Bleed within him but to gueſs, what had been the fatal Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch an Horrid Deſign, had not Gods good Providence, which hath all along been ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101388:6"/>watchful over our Soveraign, Blaſted and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated it) yet, is not all this Wickedneſs ſaid to have been contrived, and reſolved upon out of great love to, and concern for the Proteſtant Religion and Liberty of the Subject, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure us from Popery and Slavery? They, good Men! deſigned nothing but what was honeſt, for the Intereſt of Religion and the Nation, no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what the Means were, that were uſed in ſo good a Cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In nomine Domini incipit omne malum,</hi> and I think I may truly ſay, that neither Ambition nor Covetouſneſs, nor Pride, nor Revenge, nor Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, nor any other Luſt or Paſſion, that uſeth to animate Men to make Publick Diſturbances, have yet been the cauſe of ſo much Diſorder and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief in the World, as hath been occaſion'd by a Popiſh or Fanatick Zeal for Religion and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and perhaps more Evil hath been done that Good might come of it, than upon any other pretence or account whatſoever.</p>
            <p>This indeed is a weakneſs that moſt Men are more or leſs ſubject unto: When they are once ſecure of the goodneſs of the Cauſe they are ingaged in, and of the greatneſs and neceſſity of the End they propound to themſelves, their Eyes are ſo wholly fixed upon it, that they eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101388:6"/>leſs wary and ſollicitous about the Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Means they uſe for the compaſſing of it, and are apt in their heat to outrun or tranſgreſs the limits of their Duty. As it is with one who eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follows his ſport or game, when he is in cloſe purſuit he ſticks not at any bad road, he leaps over all that is in his way, and will ride over thoſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous places, which at another time he would with the greateſt care have avoided. So is it with men, whom a blind Zeal, not cool Reaſon or ſober Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion moves, they are rid by an headſtrong impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous paſſion, which violently hurries them through thick and thin, through lawful and unlawful; they ſwallow any Camel, ſo that they may at laſt obtain what they ſo earneſtly deſire. <hi>Let us do evil, that good may come, whoſe damnation is juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this Argument, I ſhall firſt of all explain the Propoſition, <hi>That we muſt not do any evil, that good may come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall prove it to you, and give you ſome Reaſons to eſtabliſh you in the belief of it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, draw ſome ſeaſonable Inferences from it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Explication of this Propoſition, <hi>That we muſt not do any evil, that good may come,</hi> there need not many words.</p>
            <p>By good here I underſtand whatever it is that is deſirable or for our advantage, either conſidered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101388:7"/>as Men or as Chriſtians, whether it relates to this life or next, whether it be publick or private, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral or ſpiritual, whether it be our own or others; for the procuring of any, or all theſe good things, we muſt not do any thing that is evil.</p>
            <p>What we call Evil is of two ſorts, either Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or Moral, or as it uſeth commonly to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, the evil of pain, or the evil of ſin; and of this latter, of ſins are theſe words only to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. As for the former, outward temporal evils, which concern our Bodies or Eſtates, they muſt be chearfully endured and undergone in a good Cauſe, for a great End, rather than omit a neceſſary Duty, or commit a plain Sin; there being more real evil in ſin, than in any outward pain or calamity that can befall us.</p>
            <p>Now of things ſinful, of which only I diſcourſe, ſome are always ſuch in all Circumſtances; other things there are which are in their own Nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, but are evil and ſinful only becauſe they are forbidden by ſome poſitive <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which therefore in a caſe of great neceſſity or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, may be done for the ſake of ſome good that follows. As we all know <hi>David</hi> and thoſe that were with him, to ſave themſelves from periſhing by hunger, did eat of the Shew-bread, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe was not lawful for them to eat, and yet were not blamed for it.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101388:7"/>
            <p>Be pleaſed therefore to obſerve, that I ſpeak not now of the violation of ſuch <hi>poſitive Commands of God,</hi> as they are commonly called, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath declared are to give place to Works of mercy and doing good to our Brother; the breach of them in ſuch caſes not being ſinful; <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf diſpenſing with thoſe Laws in ſuch extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: But I ſpeak now of things in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and intrinſically evil, and which are forbid by <hi>God</hi> becauſe they are ſuch; not the leaſt thing which is evil in its own nature may be done, tho' for the procuring the greateſt good. Which I ſhall endeavour,</p>
            <p n="2">2. To make out to you by Arguments drawn from theſe four heads. Firſt from the nature of moral good and evil. Secondly, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of <hi>Gods</hi> Providence. Thirdly, from the example of <hi>Gods</hi> Condemning and Puniſhing evil Actions, tho' donewith good Intention. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from the pernicious Conſequences of ſuch a Conceſſion as this, that we may do evil for a good End.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This will appear from the nature of moral good and evil. It is an old Maxim you may have often heard of, <hi>Bonum oritur ex cauſa inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra, malum ex quolibet defectu.</hi> To denominate an action morally good, there muſt be an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101388:8"/>Concurrence of all Conditions requiſite there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>It muſt be good as to the Object or Matter, the End for which it is done muſt be laudable and worthy; it muſt be done after a right manner, in due Circumſtances, or elſe the Action cannot be ſaid to be good. But now it is not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that it ſhould fail in every one of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to make it evil; but a defect in any one of them certainly vitiates the action, denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates it morally evil, tho' in all other reſpects it be according to the Rule.</p>
            <p>If the Object be lawful, the manner of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance regular, and it be fitly circumſtantiated, yet if it be done for a baſe, low, wicked End, this undoubtedly quite mars and ſpoils the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and renders it ſinful; and for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, let the Intention be never ſo good and honeſt, the End we propound to our ſelves never ſo great and excellent, yet if we fail in the Object, if the thing we do is forbid by Gods Law, the Action, notwithſtanding the ſpecious pretence of the glorious End to which it is directed, is a vicious Action, and we are accountable to God for it as ſuch.</p>
            <p>This a great Biſhop of our Church illuſtrates thus: <hi>Any one ſhort Clauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>or Proviſo not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101388:8"/>Legal, is ſufficient to abate the whole Writ or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, tho' in every other part abſolute and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception.</hi> A good Intention therefore can no more warrant an Action that is in it ſelf unlawful, than the goodneſs of the Matter can juſtifie what is done on a wicked Deſign.</p>
            <p>Nay further, ſuch is the contrariety between the nature of good and evil, that what is really evil cannot be choſen as a fit means to produce any thing that is good, any more than darkneſs can beget light, or than falſe Premiſes can rightly infer a true Concluſion, or than (to uſe our Saviours Phraſe) <hi>an evil Tree can bring forth good Fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> indeed (as I have already hinted) by his Omnipotent Wiſdom doth produce good out of evil, by the ſame word of Power by which he brought ſomething out of nothing; by which he can make things act contrary to their own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and proper Efficacy. But to do that which is really evil, in order to the obtaining of ſome real good, is as if a Man ſhould put his Hands into the flame to cool it; or it is juſt like the policy of thoſe Men, who would deſtroy the preſent Government to preſerve our Rights and Properties, and would pull down the Reformed Church of <hi>England</hi> for the defence of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:101388:9"/>2. I argue further, that to do evil that good may come, is a great affront to, and diſtruſt of the Divine Providence and Government of the World. So ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> cap. 13.7. <hi>Will ye ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him?</hi> Doth he ſtand in need of our ſins to help him out at a dead lift to bring his deſigns to paſs? Hath not he taken ſufficient care of, and made ſufficient proviſion for us, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we now and then ſtretch our Conſciences in a caſe of extremity? Cannot he uphold his Church or preſerve his Religion, without our venturing on a ſpecial occaſion to ſtrain a Point, and tranſgreſs our Duty for the ſake of them? Was he overſeen in the making of his Laws, not conſidering at firſt thoſe inconveniences that might ſometimes hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen? As if what he had Commanded us might prove inconſiſtent with his own Glory, or the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Safety of Religion, unleſs we in great prudence diſpenſed with his Laws in ſuch Caſes. Now this is not only a bold infringement of the Divine Authority, but alſo an unworthy Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the Wiſdom of Gods Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>This is evidently ſeen in thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who fondly imagining that our Saviour and his Apoſtles had not wrought Miracles enough for Confirmation of their Doctrine, have coined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101388:9"/>of other Miracles, which they obtrude upon their eaſy Diſciples as true, by them to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply what was wanting in our Saviours. So leſt Hell and everlaſting Damnation ſhould not be ſufficient to ſcare Men from their ſins, they have added that gainful Invention of their Purgatory. Which <hi>pious frauds</hi> (as they ſometimes call them) are moſt highly diſhonourable to our Saviour and his Religion, intimating as if his Goſpel had been very ſhort and imperfect, unleſs ſome Men had interpoſed their own Wit and Knavery to patch it up or compleat it.</p>
            <p>Thus the Laws of our Chriſtianity plainly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us not to reſiſt Lawful Authority: But alas! This may poſſibly prove very dangerous Doctrine. What if the King turns Papiſt or Tyrant? What then ſhall become of our Religion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, if in no caſe we may reſiſt, if we have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remedy but Prayers and Tears; if we are bound patiently and meekly to ſuffer thoſe evils, that may unjuſtly and contrary to Law be inflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us by that Authority we are ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? And ſo to prevent this inconvenience, Men chooſe to correct the Rule of their Religion, to diſtinguiſh away Gods Law, rather than to truſt God with their Lives and Fortunes and Religion, in the reſolved doing of their Duty.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101388:10"/>
            <p>Let us but ſuppoſe God to have done Wiſely, and acted Conſiderately in all that he hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or Forbidden us, and it muſt then neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily follow, that we muſt never go againſt his Will, tho' it may ſeem to tend to never ſo great or good an End. Since he, who had a perfect Knowledge and Comprehenſion of all Events that either can or ſhall happen in the World, hath preſcribed us ſuch Laws by which we are always to govern our ſelves, for any one to think to pleaſe him, or to promote his Glory and Service by acting contrary to theſe, is ſurely the greateſt preſumption a Creature can be Guilty of, and a foul imputation and diſparagement caſt upon the Wiſdom of God.</p>
            <p>When People are for taking the Church and Goſpel out of Gods Hands into their own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular regard, and will not think their Religion ſafe whilſt they defend it only by ſuch means as God allows of, unleſs they have ſome Tricks and Policies of their own, this certainly argues a baſe diſtruſt of the Divine Care and Providence.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Add to this the Examples that are in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of Gods Condemning and Puniſhing what hath been done againſt his Command, tho' with a good intention, and for a great and worthy end. I ſhall mention but two Inſtances, one out of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101388:10"/>
               <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> the other out of the <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> (not to inſiſt on that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable one of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah,</hi> who dyed for ſaving the tottering Ark from falling) you find <hi>King Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. receiving Commandement from God by the mouth of <hi>Samuel</hi> to deſtroy all the Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Amalec.</hi> He very zealouſly ſets about the work, and at firſt deſtroys all, both Men, and Women, and Cattel, according to the word of the Prophet. But afterwards it comes into his head, that this waſte was needleſly made, and for the ſins of Men why ſhould ſo many goodly Cattel be loſt? He reſolves therefore with himſelf to ſave the beſt and fatteſt of them, to offer them for a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God, when he return'd home with Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. He thought he could order things a better way, that it would be more for the Glory of God for theſe Cattel to ſmoke in Sacrifice upon his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, than to be deſtroyed in a ſtrange Country. This one Act of Diſobedience to a particular Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of God, notwithſtanding the Piety of his Intention, coſt him his Kingdom. <hi>Behold, to obey is better than Sacrifice, and to hearken than the fat of Rams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Example I ſhall give out of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhall be that of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who out of great love to, and forward Zeal for his Maſter, when
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101388:11"/>our Bleſſed Lord was apprehended by the Miniſters and Officers of the Chief Prieſts and Elders, <hi>drew his Sword, and ſtruck a Servant of the High Prieſts, and ſmote off his Ear.</hi> It was done in defence of Chriſt himſelf; of the moſt perfect Innocence that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appeared in the World. It was againſt unjuſt violence. His Sword was certainly drawn upon a more plauſible pretence, than any can happen in our Days: Yet mark, I beſeech you, our Saviours rebuke of him, St. <hi>Math.</hi> 26.52. <hi>Put up again thy Sword into his place, for all they that take the Sword ſhall periſh with the Sword.</hi> Do nothing contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Law, reſiſt not Authority, though it be to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Life of thy Lord and Saviour. <hi>For all they that take the Sword,</hi> who draw or uſe it, when it is not put into their Hands by thoſe that bear the Sword, by the Supreme Magiſtrate who hath the Power of the Sword, <hi>ſhall periſh by the Sword,</hi> fall themſelves by it, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncur the puniſhment of Death.</p>
            <p>That which is uſually objected in this Caſe, is the Example of others mentioned in Holy Scripture, who doing things not ſtrictly juſtifiable, ſome things plainly againſt Gods revealed Will, yet have not been Condemned, nay ſeem to be Commended for them, on the account of the Goodneſs of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or the Effect which hath followed. To which I ſhall return theſe two general Anſwers.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101388:11"/>1. That the Caſe is not the ſame with us now, as it was with thoſe who lived before the Law given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> or as it was with the <hi>Jews</hi> under the Law. We are now to govern our ſelves only by the written Will of God, not expecting nor attending to any private motions, or incitations, or ſuggeſtions, eſpecially when they lead to any thing contrary to what is Revealed to us. But it was not ſo before our Saviours time, when God did often diſcover his Mind, and give his Commands to private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by ſpecial Revelations to them, exciting and moving them to ſome particular Actions, which are no otherwiſe warrantable, than as they were done at the inſtigation, and by the direction of God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Such were <hi>Moſes</hi>'s killing the <hi>Aegyptian, Phineas</hi>'s ſlaying <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cobsi</hi> in their unclean Embraces, <hi>Ehuds</hi> ſtabbing King <hi>Eglon, Elijahs</hi> conſuming by fire from Heaven the Meſſengers whom the King ſent to apprehend him; theſe and the like Actions are no more Exemplary to us, without infallible aſſurance of the ſame Divine impulſe by which theſe Perſons were guided and acted, than <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering up his Son <hi>Iſaac,</hi> or the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſpoiling the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> of their Jewels, can now juſtifie the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of our Children, or the Robbing of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101388:12"/>
            <p>Nay, ſhould any one of us have any ſuch ſtrong motion or inſtinct upon his Spirit, inclining him to do any ſuch Action, he ought not to compare it with the private Commands given to thoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, but if it prompt him to any thing forbidden by Gods Law, or that belongs not to his Place and Calling, he ought utterly to reject it as a Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal temptation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for other Actions recorded in Scripture, that were evil in themſelves, but yet were done for a good End, (where there was not this private Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Warrant) they were neither commendable in them who did them, (tho' otherwiſe very Good and Pious Perſons) nor are they by any means imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table by us. I ſhall Inſtance in the famous caſe of <hi>Lot,</hi> when he entertained the Angels; who offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Daughters to the impure <hi>Sodomites, Gen.</hi> 19.8. that by them he might Redeem his Gueſts from the violation intended to them. Now tho' he was a ſingular good Man, and highly in favour with God, yet it muſt, I think, be ſaid that this was a fault in him, and he ought to the utmoſt hazard of his life, have defended both his Daughters Chaſtity, and his Gueſts too; and the proſtituting of one to ſecure the other, was not juſtifiable in him.</p>
            <p>The ſame muſt, I think, be ſaid of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Midwives. They were loth to obey the bloody
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101388:12"/>Edict of King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and choſe rather to tell a lye than commit ſuch Barbarity as they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, tho' in ſtrictneſs they ſhould have done neither, but peremptorily refuſed to have obeyed the King in this Matter, whatever outward evil they had ſuffered for it; and when it is ſaid, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi> 1.20. <hi>Therefore God dealt well with the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives:</hi> It is to be underſtood that he rewarded them for their tenderneſs and compaſſion towards the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Children, but not for the lye by which they excuſed themſelves to <hi>Pharaoh. Non eſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munerata fallacia ſed benevolentia: benignitas mentis, non iniquitas mentientis.</hi> All this I ſay, ſuppoſing theſe Women told a lye tho' ſome have quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe interpreted their Words.</p>
            <p>The hardeſt Caſe that I can think of is this of ſpeaking an officious untruth; when by a falſhood I may ſave the life of one or more Innocent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of my Prince, of my Father, or preſerve my Country, or the like. This for ſo great an End I ſuppoſe the beſt Caſuiſts do allow, but then it is not becauſe they judge it at any time Lawful to do Evil, or to tell a lye, that Good may come, but becauſe they judge ſuch an Officious untruth not to have in it the compleat Nature of a Lye, nor to be really Evil.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, the Examples of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101388:13"/>Holy Men of Old, whoſe Praiſes are mentioned in Scripture, ought not to be followed by us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out comparing them with the Rule of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and whatever our Lord and Saviour hath plainly forbidden us, we are upon no exigence or neceſſity of Affairs to do it, whatever End it may ſerve, or whoever hath done it before us.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And laſtly, I argue from the ill Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſuch a Conceſſion as this, that evil may be done for a good End. This one Principle ſets us free from all Authority either Divine or Humane, and every one may do whatever he thinks fit, ſo his Intention and End be but good.</p>
            <p>What we are to do, or what we are to avoid, if this Doctrine be admitted for true, we are not to learn from Gods Law commanding the one, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding the other, but then every Man, according to his own Prudence, is to judge of Things and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by their Conveniency and Expediency to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Glory of God and publick Benefit; and ſo they are either Good or Evil according as they ſeem to us, and our own Judgment and Opinion is the meaſure of lawful and unlawful, and thus we are wholly (at leaſt as to the Choice of Means) our own Maſters and Law-givers.</p>
            <p>Nay this Principle plainly overthrows all Juſtice and Faith amongſt Men, all Peace and Security in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101388:13"/>Societies, and makes all Government precarious and inſignificant, ſince every one is an Arbitrary Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and may obey or reſiſt the Laws and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtutions of his Superiours, as they appear to himſelf to be for or againſt the common good, of which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſon muſt judge for himſelf; and every mans Life, Eſtate, and Fortune is at my diſpoſal, if once I think it moſt for the Glory of God, and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion, that they ſhould be taken away.</p>
            <p>You know our Saviour tells his Diſciples of ſome that ſhould ariſe, who would think <hi>they did God good ſervice in killing of them.</hi> According to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, St. <hi>Paul</hi> was very innocent when he was ſo mad againſt the Church, and breathed forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Slaughter and Deſtruction againſt the Chriſtians: The Gun-powder Traytors deſerved to be Sainted, the Murtherers of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, and all our late Plotters of both ſorts were Martyrs, if a good End or Intention would ſanctify an evil action. But this is ſufficient in ſo plain a matter.</p>
            <p>What remains is only to draw ſome few Inferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from what I have already Diſcourſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hence we may learn what is the true meaning of that Rule that is commonly given to direct our Practice, that <hi>Of two evils the leaſt is to be choſen,</hi> which holds good only in theſe two Caſes.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:101388:14"/>1. When two or more outward Evils are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to us, and we muſt undergo one of them, ordinarily we may chuſe that which is leaſt. This was the perplexity <hi>David</hi> was reduced unto, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. after he had ſo grievouſly offended God by numbering the People. God ſent to him by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and put it to his choice, <hi>whether ſeven years of famine ſhould come into his land, or he would flee three months before his Enemies, or there ſhould be three days Peſtilence?</hi> Here <hi>David</hi> choſe the laſt, as the leaſt, ſaying, <hi>Let us fall now into the hands of the Lord; for his mercies are great, and not into the hands of men.</hi> Thus a private evil is to be ſuffered rather than the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick be endangered; and <hi>Caiaphas</hi> ſaid true, tho' he applied it ill, that it was better one man ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer than the whole Nation periſh. Thus the moſt Tyrannical and Arbitrary Government is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before none at all, and to be oppreſſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Lawful Power, is better than Civil War and Confuſion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When two Evils are propounded to us, the one of Pain, which concerns our outward Bodies or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, the other ſomething to be done that is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſinful, here we muſt chuſe the greateſt outward loſs or trouble, rather than commit the leaſt Sin; and this is our Wiſdom ſo to do; a leſs Evil, when by it we avoid a greater, having in it the nature of Good.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101388:14"/>
            <p>This was the Rule the Primitive Chriſtians pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed and ſuffered by; when the ſevereſt Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the cruelleſt Tortures, nay, not the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Death it ſelf in its uglieſt viſage, could ever make them conſent to do any thing unworthy of their holy Profeſſion. And there is nothing that redounds more to the Glory of God, and the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Religion, than the couragious ſuffering of Evil for Righteouſneſs ſake, infinitely more than the doing of any Evil, for the ſake of our Religion, can ever effect. In theſe two Caſes this Rule holds good. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. In another Caſe, which is ſometimes put, and to which this Rule is applied, it doth not hold at all. That is, when two Evils are propounded to us, both of them ſinful, but one of neceſſity to be done, what muſt we do in this Caſe? May we chuſe the leſs Sin to avoid the greater?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer; no certainly. In this Caſe we muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void both, and that it can never be allowed to commit a leſs Sin to avoid a greater, appears ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently from this one Reaſon, that if it were ſo, it would then be in the power of any Man to commit what Sin ſoever he pleaſed. For if I have a ſpite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any private Perſon, and would take away his Life, it is but Swearing or Vowing that I will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kill the King or him. Now it being a leſs ſin
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101388:15"/>to kill any private man than the King, according to this Rule of chuſing the leaſt ſin, it would become lawful to do it; and by the ſame Artifice I might make any ſin I had a mind to commit innocent and allowable, by bringing it into Competition with a greater ſin.</p>
            <p>But if two or more ſins are propounded to us, when we can chuſe any of them, we muſt chuſe none, nor can there be any ſuch real caſe wherein a man is under a neceſſity of committing ſome ſin or other, nor can any Circumſtances make it ſafe or adviſeable to venture on the leaſt ſin. So that in this inſtance this Rule, that of two Evils, that is of two ſins, the leaſt is to be choſen, does not hold.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From what I have ſaid I would take occaſion to intreat you all to beware of being led into, or ingaged in any Factious or Seditious Courſes, by the ſpecious pretences of Ambitious or Diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men. For the carrying on any evil Plot againſt the Publick, it is abſolutely neceſſary that the true Ends be concealed, and ſuch offered to open view as may be moſt apt to take with the generality of men. An outward form of Godlineſs muſt be put on by all thoſe, who intend any very miſchievous and black deſign, by which they may gain Credit and good Eſteem to themſelves, and procure grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Countenance and Reputation to their Party.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101388:15"/>
            <p>Never almoſt was there any great Sedition, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, or Rebellion contrived, or brought to any Fortunate ſucceſs, but by men pretending to grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Zeal for, and Care of Gods Honour, and love to Religion, and hatred of Errors and Abuſes, and concern for the Peoples good, and for preſerving their juſt rights, than other men; tho' all this while they ſecretly intend the inſlaving of them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturning all Law and Order: by which fair glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing ſhews and diſguiſes, <hi>they deceive, if poſſible, the very Elect,</hi> men otherwiſe ſober and Loyal.</p>
            <p>At the beginning of our late troubles here in <hi>England,</hi> had thoſe who ſet on foot, and afterwards continued that unnatutal Rebellion, at firſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told the world what they aimed at, the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Ancient Monarchy, the taking away the Kings life, and baniſhing his Children, ſetting up themſelves, and ſubjecting the whole Nation to the power of the Sword; had this deſign been but ſmelt and ſuſpected at firſt, it had in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability been cruſhed and defeated, as ſoon as diſcovered and believed. At firſt therefore nothing was talked of, but Religion, pure Ordinances, liberty of Conſcience, Freedom from Popiſh Innovations and Antichriſtian Ceremonies, true Goſpel worſhip, a preaching Miniſtry, and when by ſuch preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Artifices many were engaged to their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101388:16"/>ſide, then by degrees they began to appear in their own proper colours.</p>
            <p>And have we not been lately in great danger of being cheated and undone the ſecond time by the ſame Arts, and Fears, and Jealouſies, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Reformation, and Religion, and almoſt by the ſame men too? And may we not at laſt hope, that this repeated Experience will open mens eyes, that they may ſee what tools they have been made by deſigning heads, how they have been cajoled and impoſed upon by fair pretences; and ſome perhaps honeſt men, ſo I would in charity believe, in the ſimplicity of their hearts, made uſe of to ſerve the moſt horrid and treaſonable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, which they never thought of, or little ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected were driving on.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And eſpecially, Let us all now be exhorted to take great care that our Zeal for Religion never tranſport us beyond the bounds of our Duty.</p>
            <p>Religion is certainly the greateſt intereſt and concernment of Mankind. Dearer it ought to be to us than our lives, for infinitely more than our lives are worth depend upon it. And of all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Religions that are profeſſed in the World, I am in my Conſcience perſwaded, that which is taught here, and maintained in our Church of <hi>England</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed, is moſt Divine,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101388:16"/>moſt Chriſtian, moſt Apoſtolical and Primitive, moſt Pure and Rational, and for the continuance of this Ineſtimable Bleſſing of God amongſt us, and to our Poſterity after us (of which we have been for ſo long time thro' Gods Infinite Patience to us poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed) for this we ought ſurely to be very Zealous. No lover of God, or his own Soul, or his Country, can be indifferent or careleſs about ſuch a Matter. And as for my own part I do profeſs to have, ſo am I ſure all true Orthodox Sons of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> muſt have, as ill thoughts and as great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the Popiſh, as of any other Sect whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that calls it ſelf Chriſtian. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is undoubtedly the moſt corrupt and degenerate part of the Viſible Church of Chriſt now upon Earth; and I thank God it is my Reſolution, and it is the Reſolution of all true and hearty Members of our Church, and I pray God give us all Grace to ſtand to it, if ever we be put upon the tryal; I ſay it is our Reſolution to part with all that this World calls Dear, even Life it ſelf, rather than ever own their Novel Articles for true, or ſubmit to their U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpations, or Communicate in their Idolatrous Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But yet for all this, neither for the Preſervation of this our moſt Holy and Excellent Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed here in <hi>England,</hi> nor for the keeping out Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101388:17"/>it ſelf, (and then I have named the worſt thing that I can) will I ever, by the Grace of God, go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Duty of my Calling, and that Station Divine Providence hath placed me in, nor will I ever lift up my Finger, nor open my Mouth againſt the Lords Anointed, whatever his Religion may be, whether he hath any or none, whether he be a <hi>Nero</hi> or a <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> whether he Rules by Law or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. We muſt not wiſh him Evil, no not ſo much as in our ſecret thoughts, whatever hard things we ſuffer from him; we muſt on no account diſturb or oppoſe his Government, or reſiſt his Authority, and if we have not opportunity of flying from ſuch a Perſecution, (as I now ſuppoſe, becauſe I would put the worſt Caſe that can happen) or cannot by prudence decline it, I know no other remedy the Goſpel allows us, but Meek and Patient Suffering for our Religion, after the Example of our Bleſſed Lord and Maſter.</p>
            <p>This is the plain Loyal Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which her Miniſters have always Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Defended, both againſt Papiſts and Fanaticks of all ſorts, and for which ſuch an Out-cry and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of late Years hath been raiſed againſt the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. And whenever we Teach you otherwiſe, give me leave in Gods Name to charge you all to forſake us, and deſpiſe us at as high a rate as our greateſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101388:17"/>Enemies now can do. Nay, if an Angel from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven preach any other Doctrine, let him be accurſed.</p>
            <p>Zeal for the beſt and the greateſt things in the World will not excuſe private mens taking upon themſelves to reform publick abuſes, either againſt, or without the conſent of the Supreme Magiſtrate, nor will it hallow any action for which we have not ſufficient Warrant and Authority from Gods word. Ye remember the Anſwer which our Saviour gave to his Diſciples, when they called for Fire from Heaven to conſume that Village of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> that would not receive their Maſter, <hi>Ye know not what manner of Spirit you are of.</hi> They were much miſtaken when they thought they might do as <hi>Elias</hi> had done; that was no waies agreeable to that Meek and Lowly Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which our Saviours Doctrine was to beget in men, or to that taking up his Croſs which our Lord called his Diſciples unto, or to that Patience and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution in ſuffering, by which Chriſtianity was to be propagated and glorified in the World.</p>
            <p>For Concluſion of all, would we engage Gods Favour and Protection, that he ſhould continue to us thoſe ſingular Mercies we yet enjoy; let us then at all times adhere cloſe to our Duty, as well when it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our temporal Intereſt, as when it is for it. Let us inviolably in all things obſerve the Commands of our Religion, not only propound good ends, but be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101388:18"/>as careful to chuſe Lawful means, and then God w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in ſome meaſure think himſelf as it were obliged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhew Mercy and Favour to us.</p>
            <p>If ever any thing provokes God Almighty t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bring thoſe Calamities upon us, which we ſeem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much to fear, it is our uſing indirect unlawful mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to prevent their falling upon us. And is it not thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with us at this day? For could our Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>my, I mean the Papiſts, have ever invented a mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſucceſsful Plot for the bringing in of Popery? could they have hoped for a better opportunity, or great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er advantages, for the recommending and introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their Religion, than what the abominable Wickedneſs and Treaſons of thoſe who would be accounted the greateſt Zealots againſt it, have now given them? By doing of ſuch horrid Evils, under pretence that good may come, have they not given the greateſt Blow and Wound to the Reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and done their beſt to bring that miſery up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, which they would be thought to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to have kept off?</p>
            <p>The Lord ſtill in his infinite Mercy continue to preſerve our moſt Gracious Soveraign, and the Church, and theſe Kingdoms, from all either ſecret Conſpiracies, or open Aſſaults of Wicked Men, of what Sect or Denomination ſoever, who think it Lawful <hi>to do evil, that good may come, whoſe damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is juſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
